Guide to the Robert G. Dunbar Papers 1930-1986
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Robert G. Dunbar papers
1930-1986
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Dunbar, Robert G.
2437
4 linear feet
The Robert G. Dunbar Papers consist of research materials that include copies of journal articles, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, maps, syllabi, bibliographies, assorted transcriptions of research, topical notes on history organized by places, periods and subjects, class lecture outlines, and lecture notes from both his personal college courses and courses taught during his teaching career. Also included are papers compiled for publications, speeches, and research on agricultural history, papers related to his activities on the Curriculum and Instruction Committee, as Director for the Center for Inter-Cultural Affairs, founder of the International Studies Center, establishment of a Peace Corps program (Ecuador/Heifer), and the International Farm Youth Exchange program. Other materials include transcripts of various reviews, and correspondence from Dunbar's affiliation with organizing the Great Plains Foundation and The Montana Farmers Union. Additionally there are copies of some publications, miscellaneous files including one on the Dead Sea Scrolls and ephemera.
One file of recommendations for students and colleagues to educational institutions, organizations and government programs. Restricted until the year 2050.
The bulk of Robert G. Dunbar's Papers were donated by the Department of History and Philosophy of Montana State University - Bozeman in 2000. Several smaller accessions were incorporated into the collection: Collections 1166, 1168, 1266, 1367, 1402, 2088 were donated by Robert G. Dunbar from 1974-1984, and Collection 1154 was donated by Edward J. Bell and Robert G. Dunbar in 1985.
Robert Dunbar's papers have been organized into five series with his individual files maintained as much as possible as he originally created them. Dunbar frequently reused paper so a great deal of his hand written and typed notes are on the reverse side of other materials. Care has been taken to retain the order and integrity of this material as much as possible. Correspondence was distributed both within relevant files and chronologically in a set of general files.
Series 1: Teaching Files, 1930-1971
Series 2: Research Files, 1936-1983
Subseries 1: Publications Research, 1940-1983
Subseries 2: Speeches, Addresses and Talks, 1936-1969
Subseries 3: Agricultural History and Organizations Research, undated
Series 3: Montana State University Development and Programs, 1948-1972
Series 4: Agricultural Organization mMmbership, 1949-1980
Series 5: Bibliography, Professional and Personal Correspondence, and Ephemera, 1937-1986
Robert George Dunbar was born April 30, 1907 in La Grange, Wisconsin. He married Mary Snell Albertson in 1937 and had two children. He received a B.A. in History with a minor in Spanish from Milton College in Wisconsin in 1929. In 1933 he received his M.A. in History from the University of Wisconsin and earned his PhD in 1935, also from the University of Wisconsin. He taught at the University of South Dakota in Vermillion, 1935-1937 and at Colorado State University at Fort Collins, 1937-1947. During World War II, he served in the U.S. Navy as an instructor at Navy War Orientations Programs in Bainbridge, MD. He joined the faculty of the History Department at Montana State University in 1947. He was an Associate Professor of History from 1948-1950 and Professor of History from 1950-1973. He served as Director of the Center for Inter-Cultural Affairs from 1968-1973. At M.S.U. he also founded the International Studies Center in 1955, and in 1963, he succeeded in establishing a Peace Corp training program focused on helping agricultural projects in Ecuador. He was an authority on water rights and irrigation in the Western United States. He was the author of Forging New Rights in Western Waters (University of Nebraska Press, 1983); The Farmer and the American Way (Oxford Book Company,1952); "History of Agriculture;" chapter 5 of vol. 2, in Colorado and Its People (Lewis Historical Pub. Co, 1948); "History of Agriculture;" chapter 12, of vol. 1, in A History of Montana, by Merrill G. Burlingame and K. Ross Toole (Lewis Historical Pub. Co., 1957) and numerous articles in professional journals and newspapers. He served as president of the American Agricultural Society, 1966-67 and spoke frequently to national and state agricultural groups. He vigorously advocated inter-cultural programs and Native American Education. He was a founding member of the Bozeman Chapter of the Unitarian Universalist Fellowship, which bears his name. Upon retirement in 1974, he was awarded the rank of Professor Emeritus in History. Dr. Dunbar died February 15, 1993 at age 85.
The Robert Dunbar papers consist of research, drafts, and speeches documenting to his teaching career and academic scholarship. The first series contains Dunbar's teaching files and includes periodicals, pamphlets, maps, lecture notes, and syllabi related to the courses he taught. A professor of history, Dunbar taught on a wide variety of subjects including ancient civilizations, medieval Europe, modern Europe, American foreign policy, the American west, and history of agriculture.
The series two is the most extensive, and features drafts and research for Dunbar's scholarly publications, speeches, and general research on agricultural history. This series contains voluminous files related to his research for the article "The Initiation of the McNary-Haugen Movement in Montana and the Pacific Northwest," which he co-author Marguerita ("Rita") McDonald and focuses on farm relief programs in the mid-1920s. It also contains extensive research for his articles "Economic Development of the Gallatin Valley" and "History of Agriculture." Materials related to Dunbar's speeches included notes, transcripts, and correspondence. Topics of his talks include the Spanish Civil War, European conditions pre-World War II, the United Nations, and the development of the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA). He also maintained a large array of general research files on topics in agricultural history.
The last three series document to Dunbar's involvement with Montana State College (later Montana State University) activities and professional organizations. They include files related to his work with the Curriculum and Instruction Committee, as his work as Director for the Center for Inter-Cultural Affairs, founder of the International Studies Center, establishment of a Peace Corps program (Ecuador/Heifer), and involvement in the International Farm Youth Exchange program. Files on professional organizations include the Great Plains Foundation, The Montana Farmers Union, and the Agricultural History Society.
Washington, George, 1732-1799
Agricultural History Society; Great Plains Foundation; International Farm Youth Exchange; Montana Farmers Union; Montana State University--Bozeman-Administration; Montana State University--Bozeman--Faculty; Peace Corps (U.S.)
Gallatin Valley (Mont.)-Economic conditions-History
Agricultural development projects--Ecuador; Agricultural price supports--Law and legislation--United States; Agriculture--Colorado--History; Agriculture--History--Societies, etc; Agriculture--Montana--Gallatin Valley--History; Agriculture--Montana--Societies, etc; Agriculture--United States--History; Cross-cultural studies-Montana-Bozeman; Foreign study-Montana-Bozeman; History-Study and teaching (Higher)-Montana-Bozeman; Irrigation-West (U.S.)-History; Riparian rights-West (U.S.)-History; Water rights-West (U.S.)-History; College teachers--Montana--Bozeman; History teachers--Montana--Bozeman
Agriculture; Civil Procedure and Courts; Colleges and Universities; Water and Water Rights; Montana; Bozeman
Articles; Bibliographies; Research (document genres); Speeches, addresses, etc., American
- Teaching Files, 1930-1971; 1
  Files containing research notes, term papers, newspaper clippings, brochures, maps, copies of articles, lecture notes, syllabi, lecture outlines, bibliographies, collected subject files resulting from personal history courses taken and history courses taught during Mr. Dunbar' career.
  - European History - Medieval, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - European History - Old Order and Enlightened Despots, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Historical Method, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - European History - Since 1815, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American History - Representative Americans, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - German History - Ranke paper and notes, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - French Regionalism - Term Paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hellenistic Civilization (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Economic History, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Medieval Civilization, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Summer: Reformation, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Summer: American Foreign Policy, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Summer: History of the West, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - French History, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American History + 1 paper, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Recent German History, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 16th Century Art, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Economic Life, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - European 19th Century History, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - American History - Civil War, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Roman Empire, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Europe - Middle Ages, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Economics History, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Later Roman Empire, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - European History notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Modern European History, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Assorted notes and subjects, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - French and English notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scotland - Home Rule Essay, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - History 1a - Notes and Syllabi, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American History II- Teaching Notes and Aids, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - American History- Teaching Notes and Aids, Late 1940s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Army History Basic I-II - Teaching Notes and Aids, Late 1940s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - American History - Summer School - Teaching Notes and Aids, Late 1940s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - History of the West - Teaching Notes and Aids, Late 1940s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ancient History (Egypt) - Teaching Notes and Aids, Late 1940s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - History of the Pacific - Teaching Notes and Aids, Late 1940s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - History of Agriculture - Teaching Notes and Aids; Letter recommending adding course at Montana State College, 1940s, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Foreign Policy Education - Teaching Notes and Aids, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - History of Civilization 105, 106, 107 - Teaching Notes and Aids, 1954-1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Non-Western World - Teaching Notes, Aids, Student Papers, Class Evaluations, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - History of Civilization - Teaching Notes and Aids, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Guest for Curriculum Class taught by Wm. Vandiver, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - History of American Agriculture - Syllabi, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Austria (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bibliographies (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Canada (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Cathedrals (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chronology (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - England (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Europe - 1815 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Finland - Hungary - Poland (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - France (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Germany (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Historians (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Poland (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Propaganda (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Propaganda (cont.) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Russia (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Serbia (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Spain (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Foreign Newspaper Articles, 1934-1949 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Significant Headlines of World War II, 1941-1945 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - German Peace Settlement News Clippings, 1946-1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - New York Times Picture Section - Clipping with Emphasis on Europe and Nazis, 1936-1940 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Blank class-work maps, maps of Europe for different historical eras and Newsweek maps (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Newsweek maps of the week and month, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Research Files, 1936-1983; 2
  Series 2 has been arranged in 3 sub-series: 1. Research files identified with publications; "Washington the Farmer," "History of Agriculture," "The Farmer and the American Way," "The Economic Development of the Gallatin Valley," "The Initiation of the McNary-Haugen Movement in Montana and the Pacific Northwest," and "Forging New Rights in Western Waters;" 2. Research files created for speeches, talks and presentations having topics of pre-World War II conditions, the United Nations and the USDA; 3. his remaining files on agricultural history include agricultural organizations, general nature within subject areas related to his professional activities and interests.
  - Research files for published works, 1
    This subseries contains research files related to Dunbar's published scholarship. Research files identified with the following publications: "Washington the Farmer;" Western Farm Life, v. 42:3, Feb.1, 1940; "History of Agriculture;" chapter 5 of v. 2, Colorado and Its People, 1948; The Farmer and the American Way, Oxford Book Co., 1952; "The Economic Development of Gallatin County;" Pacific Northwest Quarterly, v. 47:4, Oct. 1956; "The Initiation of the McNary-Haugen Movement in Montana and the Pacific Northwest," Pacific Northwest Quarterly, v.71:2, Rita McDonald and Robert G. Dunbar, Apr. 1980; and Forging New Rights in Western Waters, University of Nebraska Press, 1983.
    Research files for "The Initiation of the McNary-Haugen Movement in Montana and the Pacific Northwest" are the most well represented in this series and feature photocopies of original reports, newspaper articles, correspondence, meeting minutes, and hearings. They also include Dunbar's notes, timelines, and bibliographies. Individuals featured in the research files include E. J. Bell, Calvin Coolidge, Dwight R. Cresap, Chester C. Davis, Hubert Edbert, Frank R. Gooding, Gilbert N. Haugen, Herbert Hoover, George J. Jewett, Edward C. Johnson, Eugene Meyer, Jr., Frank W. Mondell, Charles L. McNary, Walter J. Robinson, James S. Shideler, John W. Summers, O. F. Tate, Henry C. Taylor, Samuel R. Thompson, William L. Thompson, Henry C. Wallace, Frank J. Wilmer and M.L. Wilson. The activities of American Wheat Growers Associated, Inc., the Montana Export Commission League, the Washington Export League, the Portland Chamber of Commerce and reports of the Colfax, Washington meeting, Spokane meeting, and Meyer-Mondell mission are represented in distinct files. The remainder of these papers are research and a draft for an earlier article in 1969 on the McNary-Haugen bill by Rita McDonald, a typed set of notes, chronology of events and table of contents by Rita McDonald, drafts, critiques, footnotes, corrections of the final article, and an extensive exchange of correspondence with some enclosures between the two authors.
    There are also extensive research files for his article "Economic Development of the Gallatin Valley." These files contain collected notes on sawmills, flour mills, coal mines, creameries and agricultural businesses; interviews with Elmer Bartholomew, Walter Cooper, Donald Corcoran, C.S. Kenyon, Rex Labertew, C.B. Moore, George Morgan, George R. Porter, George P. Reller, Frank Stone, Norman L. Towne, Charles Vandenhook and Lee H. Williams; papers (Seed Pea industry and lumber industry).
    His research on Forging New Rights in Western Waters features extension bulletins, articles, transcriptions of interviews with Clarence Hinkle, Fred Hennighhausen, Herman R. Crile and John Scully, and correspondence with Albert G. Feidler, Herman R. Crile and others on water rights and irrigation
    His files for the "History of Agriculture" chapter on Colorado include research on dry land farming, fruit and melon industries, lamb and sheep rearing, potatoes, migrant workers and immigration, radicalism, suffrage, rural free delivery, and the San Luis Valley.
    - "Washington the Farmer" - various rough drafts and copy of the journal (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "History of Agriculture" - notes, draft and correspondence (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - "History of Agriculture" - miscellaneous agricultural subjects in Colorado (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "History of Agriculture" - dry land farming (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "History of Agriculture" - fruit raising (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - "History of Agriculture" - lamb and sheep rearing (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - "History of Agriculture" - melon industry (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - "History of Agriculture" - migrant workers and immigration (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "History of Agriculture" - potatoes (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - "History of Agriculture" - radicalism, suffrage and rural free delivery (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "History of Agriculture" - San Luis Valley (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - "The Farmer and the American Way" - correspondence, outline, research notes and related materials (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - "The Economic Development of the Gallatin Valley" - Assorted notes on industries lumber, mining, agriculture, milling, irrigation, and other local businesses (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "The Economic Development of the Gallatin Valley" (cont.) - more industry notes (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "The Economic Development of the Gallatin Valley" (cont.) - Interviews - industry founders and business leaders (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "The Economic Development of the Gallatin Valley" (cont.) - Papers, brochures, maps, and copy of the journal article (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "The Initiation of the McNary-Haugen Movement in Montana and the Pacific Northwest" - background (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - McNary-Haugen - biographies of some of the key individuals (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - McNary-Haugen - articles, notes, time-line, correspondence and newspaper clippings of notes, 1920s (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - McNary-Haugen - wheat situation, early 1920s (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - McNary-Haugen - wheat situation - comprehensive notes and newspaper clippings, 1920s (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - McNary-Haugen - wheat growers - organizations, clippings of reactions, etc (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - McNary-Haugen - wheat growers, organizing and problems pooling wheat (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - McNary-Haugen - American Wheat Growers Associated, Inc. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - McNary-Haugen - Colfax, Washington meeting - export commissions (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - McNary-Haugen - Idaho wheat growers, export commissions (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - McNary-Haugen - M.L. Wilson files on wheat problem - correspondence (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - McNary-Haugen - Meyer-Mondell mission - notes, report (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - McNary-Haugen - Montana Export Commission League - papers, notes, and correspondence (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - McNary-Haugen - Washington Export League organization (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - McNary-Haugen - Oregon, Washington reactions to wheat crisis, exports (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - McNary-Haugen - Portland Chamber of Commerce opposition (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - McNary-Haugen - Oregon, Washington correspondence and telegrams (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - McNary-Haugen - Spokane meeting (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - McNary-Haugen - Henry C. Taylor - interview, notes (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - McNary-Haugen - Wallace to Taylor (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - McNary-Haugen - M.L. Wilson interview (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - McNary-Haugen - Draft manuscript and related documents for earlier article by Rita McDonald in 1969 on McNary-Haugen bill (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - McNary-Haugen - Typed copy of notes, chronology of events and table of contents by Rita McDonald - date unknown (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - McNary-Haugen - Early drafts, commentary, critiques of 1980 article (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - McNary-Haugen - Draft article with footnotes, corrections of 1980 article (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - McNary-Haugen - Dunbar-McDonald correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Forging New Rights in Western Waters" - Correspondence seeking information on research sources in irrigation and water rights, 1948-1981 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "Forging New Rights in Western Waters" (cont.) - Papers, bulletins, brochures, articles pamphlets, 1889-1974 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - "Forging New Rights in Western Waters" (cont.) - Interviews, typed or longhand, 1973-1979 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Speeches, addresses and talks, 1936-1969; 2
    This subseries contains research files created for Dunbar's speeches or addresses. They include two speeches to unknown audience on the Spanish Civil War and conditions in Europe 1936, a talk to the Rotary Club - 1939; a Farmer-Labor Institute talk, 1958; several talks on the United State Department of Agriculture (USDA), 1964-69; and a United Nations Day address, 1961.
    - Pre-World War II speeches on Spain and European conditions - transcripts, notes, and correspondence (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Rotary talk of 1939 on war and if US will stay out - hand-written transcript (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Farmer-Labor Institute talk on the U.N. and taxes, 1958 - clippings, correspondence, notes and various printed support documents (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - United Nations Day address, 1961 - research documents and supporting print materials, correspondence, newspaper clippings and transcripts (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - USDA talks, 1964-1969 - correspondence, transcripts, clippings and other support materials (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Agricultural history and organizations, 3
    This subseries contains Dunbar's general research files on agricultural history. These files feature bibliographies, notes, copies of journal articles, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, essays, maps, brochures, transcriptions of interviews and correspondence. These files cover research on Montana agricultural history, the Farm Bureau, National Farmers Organization, National Farmers Union, Non-Partisan League, Grange, Equity, Farmers Alliance, the Land Grant College System, water resources, climate, crops and livestock, the American frontier and westward movement, machinery, land policy, snow surveys, and rural sociology. Special topics include the Holland Settlement in Montana, Fairway Farm Project, Kinsey Flats/Case-Wheeler Projects, M. L. Wilson - taped remembrances of Edward Bell and Dr. Robert Dunbar, and the seed pea industry in Gallatin County, Montana.
    Transcriptions of interviews include Jack Taylor, Hobart E. Myrick, Mildred K. Stoltz, E. A. Willson, Elmer Starch and John G. Parker; addresses by Roland R. Renne and R. G. Dunbar.
    Also included are materials on Napoleonic France, Europe, and sundry topics of historical interest. The files were not identifiable as related to any particular work product of Robert Dunbar's but were used for publications, lectures, talks, speeches and conferences. The files have been arranged alphabetically by topic. * (These items filed with audio/visual materials).
    - Agricultural history - bibliographies (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Agricultural history - bibliographies (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Agricultural history - general materials - foreign influences, American Indian methods (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Agricultural history - general materials - Southern agriculture, slavery (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Agricultural history - general materials - agricultural education, climate and terrain (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Agricultural history - general materials - crops, machinery (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Agricultural history - general materials - land policy, westward movement (Box 12, Folder 2)